<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Message sent from His Highness the Lord Protector, to the great Turk, with his demands and proposals; and the releasing of the English captives. Likewise, the new edict, and decree of the governor of Argier; the redeemng [sic] of all English-men from thraldom and slavery, and the bringing of them in to Gen. Blake; the seizing of the Salley men of war, and a narrative of the general proceedigns fo the English, in order to the French, Dutch, and Spainards. Extracted out of the original papers; licensed and published by special authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80951</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E820_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207346</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866403</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866403</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168010</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80951)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168010)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 125:E820[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Message sent from His Highness the Lord Protector, to the great Turk, with his demands and proposals; and the releasing of the English captives. Likewise, the new edict, and decree of the governor of Argier; the redeemng [sic] of all English-men from thraldom and slavery, and the bringing of them in to Gen. Blake; the seizing of the Salley men of war, and a narrative of the general proceedigns fo the English, in order to the French, Dutch, and Spainards. Extracted out of the original papers; licensed and published by special authority.</title>
                  <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Lord Protector (1653-1658 : O. Cromwell)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Peter Mitchel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 18.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168010:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MESSAGE SENT FROM His Highneſs the Lord Protector, <hi>TO THE</hi> GREAT TURK, <hi>WITH</hi> His Demands and Propoſals; and the releaſing of the Engliſh Captives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LIKEWISE,</hi> The new Edict, and Decree of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Argier;</hi> the redeeming of all Engliſh-men from Thraldom and Slavery, and the bringing of them in to Gen. Blake; the ſeizing of the Salley men of War, and a Narrative of the general proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Engliſh, in order to the French, Dutch, and Spaniards.</p>
            <p>EXtracted out of the Original Papers; Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and publiſhed by ſpecial Authority.</p>
            <p>London, printed for Peter Mitchel, 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="message">
            <pb facs="tcp:168010:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168010:2"/>
            <head>A Meſſage ſent from his Highneſs the Lord Protector to the Turks, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HIs Highneſs the Lord Protector having taken into ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, the moſt deplorable &amp; ſuffering condition of the poor captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Engliſh at Argier, and other places in Turky, graciouſly vouchſafed to ſend an Expreſs to the Governour of Argier, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring a Reſtauration of the Engliſh Captives; and withal, adjuring him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from any ſuch future violence, againſt the Engliſh Subjects: This Meſſage was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168010:3"/>reſented with ſo much terrour and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, that the Governour immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gave Order, for the releaſe of all the Engliſh; and ſet forth an Edict, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, prohibiting the ſeizing of any Engliſh Veſſel whatſoever, upon pain of death; and to incur the ſeizure of their whole Eſtate, in caſe of any obſtructing, or interpoſing any Engliſh man whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, in their free Trade and Commerce; &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By an Expreſs from General Blakes Fleet, thus. Sir, When we came into Cales Road, we ſaluted the Town with 21 pieces of Ordnance, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned us 7 for one, both Engliſh, Spaniards, and Hollanders. The Dutch Admiral vailed his Flag and ſaluted. Our General aſſured the Spaniards we intended nothing prejudicial to them, who before ſuſpected us. We ſailed from thence to the Straights, anchoring in Gibralter Road; where we went on ſhore, and were very courteouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Governour, who promiſed us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation in whatſoever we wanted, and the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168010:3"/>Countrey afforded: VVe were very courteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaluted by the Clergy, and had four Officers of their Army went bare before us, conducting us through the Town, and to the Cuſtome-Houſe, at the requeſt of the Goxernour, who had there provided a very ſtately Collation for us. He alſo made proclamation (having received Order from the King ſo to do) That none whatſoever ſhould affront the Engliſh upon pain of preſent Death. VVe had not been long here, but one of our Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualling ſhips (the Dolphin) who by the late ſtorms was ſeperated from us, came to us: In her way ſhe fell among 7 great French ſhips, who took her; the Admiral then called our Captain on board his ſhip (which carried 56 pieces of Braſs Ordnance) demanding of him where Gen. Blake was, and what ſtrength he had with him? He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, That he was gone to the Steights with 30 Men of VVar. The Admiral therewith was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; and proffered him a great ſum of money to ſatisfie for what his men had taken from him, and deſired him to ſtay, and he would enquire after thoſe that had plundered him, and execute them: but our Capt. refuſed both VVhereupon drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing General Blakes Health, they diſcharged him, and he came to us with all ſpeed.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:168010:4"/>
               <head>A Letter frrom the Navy.</head>
               <p>UPon our advance from Cadiz, further into the Levant ſea, VVee met with many diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, not onely by ſtomy and unſeaſonable Weather, but by ſome obſcure Rocks, which our Pylots were not very wel acquainted with: But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for ſome time waited upon the Series of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, we then immediatly found the Omnipotent workings of the moſt high Protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, and great Jehovah of Heaven for Us; who, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in an inſtant, when we were all toyling and plunging through the Deep, cauſed the winds to ceaſe, and the Seas to become calm; ſo that our whole Fleet (bleſſed be God) in few houres came within ſight of each other, who bearing up to the Ambral, our General commanded forth Captain Sacheverel with the Pearl Frigat, and Cap. George Crapnel in the Merlin Galley, as Scouts; who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 5 hours ſayl diſcovered a Fleet with French co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, conſiſting of 17 in number, which Cap Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheverel haled; but the French refuſed to anſwer: whereupon, he bare up to them, being accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by valiant Ca. Crapnel, and having the wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, gave them ſeven broad ſides; which thunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Eccho arriving the Eares of our heroick Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, he preſently bare up with the George, &amp; the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168010:4"/>reſt of the Fleet to the very head of them, &amp; charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them through and through five times together; inſomuch, that the French tack'd about, and decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Engagement; but we embraced the purſuit, &amp; in the chaſe ſunk 3, fir'd two, and took 5, which we deſerted, they being ſo leakie, that ſuddenly they ſunk alſo. The reſt fled towards Naples, where the D. of Guiſe is with his Fleet; whom we are under ſayl to viſit. But by a ſtratagem ('tis ſaid) his Highneſs, with the Lord St. Paul, and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chief Commanders, are ſurprized in the City, upon a pretence of ſurrender; in the mean time, confident I am, (by divine permiſſion) that we ſhal ſuddenly ingage them; for our men are reſolved to fight them, though they be five to one. Our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral hath ſet up the Engliſh Standard, bearing St. Georges Croſs, at the Head of all the Flag ſhips; which carries no little terror to the Pyrats in theſe parts; who abounded very much upon the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; but are now pretty well diſpierced; for we have put a period to above 100 of them within the ſpace of a month; and have taken 11 Turkiſh Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, in which Atchievment, Capain Hill with the VVorceſter Frigat, and Capt. Cattens in the Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port performed ſingular ſervice; but the Pearl loſt her Maſt, and ſome other ſhips their Bolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprit, and Tackling.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:168010:5"/>
               <p>As touching the influence the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector hath gained by his Meſſage to the Turks, 'tis a thing wonderfully to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired; and indeed, it cauſeth no little ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration throughout all Chriſtendome; for, true it is, the Argier men of War are become Aſſociates with the Engliſh, and will not permit a man of our Nation to be carryed captive into thraldome; but ſeiz and takes all their Sally ſhips, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that have any Engliſh them, and brings them in to Gen. Blake, who at this very inſtant, rides tryumphat in the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Ocean.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
